Finding Aid for Biological Station (University of Michigan) records, 1955-1991
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Biological Station (University of Michigan) records 1955-1991 1979-1989
University of Michigan. Biological Station.
0.5 linear feet
044 Bimu C 241 2
The University of Michigan Biological Station (UMBS) was established in 1909 as a teaching and research facility located in the tip of the lower peninsula of Michigan. It preserves several habitats for study. The main areas of research are field biology and ecology. The records of the UMBS focus on evaluations of the program, research, and educational programs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records (donor # 1665 ) were transferred November 2003. 1665
The record group is open without restriction.
The University of Michigan Biological Station (UMBS) was established in 1909 and is part of the College of Literature, Science and Arts. It is located on the tip of the lower peninsula of Michigan, on the shores of Douglas Lake. The UMBS encompasses many habitats, including several vegetation zones, bogs, marshes, swamps, fens, beach pools, natural undeveloped lake shoreline, lakes, and two creek watersheds. It was established to protect the land for current and future research.
The UMBS is both a teaching and research facility. It was established for summer research only but expanded to operate all year in the early 1970s to allow for more thorough study of the ecosystems. Undergraduate and graduate students attend seminars, classes, and conduct independent studies to learn how to conduct research. Professionals come to the UMBS to conduct research, and to teach. There are research facilities, teaching laboratories and classrooms, a library, and living facilities.
The research at UMBS is focused on field biology and ecology. Researchers seek to understand the habitats and ecosystems located within the UMBS. It provides a good location for studying lake, stream, and forest ecology. Other areas of research have included the physiological ecology of plants and animals, systematics, limnology, biological indicators of environmental change, and land use and management.
More current information is available at the UMBS website: http://www.umich.edu/~umbs
The records of the University of Michigan Biological Station (UMBS) include materials used to evaluate the benefit of continuing the program during a university budget crisis in the early 1980s, and materials focused more generally on the research and educational programs of the UMBS. The records are divided into four subseries: Administrative, Review, Research, and Education Programs.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Biological Station.; Ecology.; Douglas Lake (Mich.); Sleeping Bear Dunes National Lakeshore (Mich.)
- Administrative
  Material in the Administrative series consists of information describing the program and location, partial executive committee meeting minutes from 1955 to 1964, discussions regarding the budget, enrollment statistics from 1909 to 1989, and the major need assessments.
  - Background, 1964-1976 (Box 1)
    (location descriptions, research possibilities, reports on UMBS progress)
  - Biological Station Executive Committee Minutes, 1955-1964 (Box 1)
  - Changing Directors, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Justifying Budget Needs to LS&A, 1972-1983 (Box 1)
  - Sources of Funding, 1964-1985 (Box 1)
  - Enrollment Statistics (number of undergraduate, graduate and foreign students each year), 1909-1989 (Box 1)
  - Biological Station Needs, 1973 and undated
- Program Review
  The Program Review series contains records from the evaluation of the biostation program during the budget crisis in the early 1980s. There are reports on the program, correspondence, materials from the LS&A review committee, and summaries of surveys of graduate students, undergraduate students, investigators, faculty, and staff of the UMBS.
  - External Reviews, 1979-1982 (Box 1)
  - LS&A Review Committee, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence of Dean Steiner and Dr. Gates (Director of UMBS), 1981-1985 (Box 1)
  - Survey of Biological Station Residents, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Question IA: Instruction and Courses, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Question IB: Quality of Courses, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Question II: Research Facilities, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Question III: Housing and Dining Quality, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Question IV: General Satisfaction, 1982
- Research
  The Research series includes research done at the UMBS and by UMBS researchers at other locations. Materials include research proposals, contracts, and final reports. The major research projects are a vegetation survey of the Manitou Islands and Sleeping Bear Dunes, and a water quality study of Northern Michigan. There is also material regarding the formation of an Information Retrieval System for the UMBS library to facilitate access to records of past research.
  - Research Proposals, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Publication List and Researcher Specializations, 1909-1989 (Box 1)
  - Vegetation Survey (Manitou Islands, Sleeping Bear Dunes, proposal, research contract, expenses, correspondence), 1983-1989 (Box 1)
  - Vegetation Survey Final Report (The Terrestrial Vegetation and Flora of North and South Manitou Islands, Sleeping Bear Dunes National Lakeshore, Technical Report No. 11, Hazlett and VanderKopple, Includes two maps) (Box 1)
  - Water Quality in Northern Michigan, 1984-1986 (Box 1)
  - Information Retrieval System for the UMBS Library, 1981-1984
- Education Programs
  The series Education Programs consists of two programs: the Groundwater Education in Michigan program (GEM) and the Naturalist-Ecologist Training Program (NETP). GEM promotes the maintenance of water quality and includes a center located at UMBS with literature pertaining to groundwater for the education of communities, and a classroom component to teach about water quality. NETP is a training program for students located at the UMBS, which allows students to work with established ecologists and develop their knowledge and research skills. The 1983 NETP report to the Mellon foundation includes ten black and white, 5x7 inch photographs attached to the back pages of the report. Nine are of students conducting research and one is a group photograph. The photograph on page 36 is missing.
  - Groundwater Education in Michigan (GEM) Annual Progress Report), 1990-1991 (Box 1)
  - Naturalist-Ecologist Training Program (NETP)
    - Goals and policies, 1982-1986 (Box 1)
    - Evaluations by students, 1983 1985 1986 (Box 1)